<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Wild Camping | Everything Else.]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/categories/wild-camping/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-19T15:42:43+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cooking With the Alpkit BruPot]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/2015/02/16/cooking-with-the-alpkit-brupot/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-16T21:11:22+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/2015/02/16/cooking-with-the-alpkit-brupot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-f-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/1610875_10155145827370092_4684168703150899792_n.jpg?oh=a2499de429d9c3f952c0fdd452ca652a&amp;oe=558E3766&amp;__gda__=1435804726_27b6e1f160b0149330c159928f7f43b4">https://fbcdn-sphotos-f-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/1610875_10155145827370092_4684168703150899792_n.jpg?oh=a2499de429d9c3f952c0fdd452ca652a&amp;oe=558E3766&amp;__gda__=1435804726_27b6e1f160b0149330c159928f7f43b4</a>&#8221;></p>

<p><a href="https://www.alpkit.com/products/brupot">Alpkit&rsquo;s BruPot</a> got a sustained &ldquo;field test&rdquo; on my recent wild camp, combined with the <a href="http://www.vango.co.uk/gb/outdoor-essentials/386-compact-gas-stove.html#">Vango Compact Stove</a> and <a href="http://www.backpackinglight.co.uk/bushcraft/QE105.html">Primus&#8217; Wind-shield</a>. Anodised titanium cooking pot, one litre capacity, with heat exchanger on the base to maximise heating efficiency. Handles wrap round the pot during storage. Rubber lid, with drinking hole, along with an insulating cover for the sides. Marks on the inside for 250 millimetres increments make measuring water easy.</p>

<p>Pot sold standalone (£20) or with a stove in their <a href="https://www.alpkit.com/products/brukit">BruKit package</a> (£35).</p>

<p>Using in the evening and morning, boiling water for my meals and coffee, with no issues. Boiling time somewhere between five and ten minutes, wasn&rsquo;t paying particular attention, despite the very cold temperatures.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.backpackinglight.co.uk/bushcraft/QE105.html">Primus&#8217; Wind-shield</a> was another great addition to my micro-cooking setup. Slots over the gas cannister when not in use, which can both be stowed inside the BruPot.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, mini-stove is marginally too large to fit inside the BruPot with the cannister and windscreen. This extra space can be handily used for lighters, fire stick or coffee sachets.</p>

<p>This micro-cooking setup has now replaced the flask in my rucksack. Having a stove allows you to make multiple brews on a trip and even hot lunches. Weight and space differences compared to a flask seem negligible.</p>

<p><em>Extremely impressed with the BruPot. Buying outdoors gear is normally choosing two from cheap, light and robust. Alpkit&rsquo;s BruPot has all three.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Wild Camping - Brecon Beacons]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/2015/02/11/winter-wild-camping-brecon-beacons/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-11T14:16:16+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/2015/02/11/winter-wild-camping-brecon-beacons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xfa1/v/t1.0-9/10941021_10155145827240092_8942377643846403791_n.jpg?oh=236f0ca2e0caf1043f6f169e8a434587&amp;oe=5559ADD2">https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xfa1/v/t1.0-9/10941021_10155145827240092_8942377643846403791_n.jpg?oh=236f0ca2e0caf1043f6f169e8a434587&amp;oe=5559ADD2</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>With the last weekend in January approaching, there was just enough time to get this month&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com/microadventures-3/year-microadventure-2/">#microadventure</a> completed.</p>

<p>Cold weather had brought heavy snow to UK&rsquo;s mountain, perfect winter walking conditions.</p>

<p>Living in the South East, the <a href="http://www.breconbeacons.org/">Brecon Beacons</a> were my destination.</p>

<p>Rather than travelling up Saturday morning, wild camping the night before would give me an early start the next day. This would allow me to get ahead of the masses descending on Pen Y Fan during the weekend.</p>

<p>Weather forecasts for the weekend were continuing to be <em>alpine</em>, strong winds and snow expected overnight and throughout the following day. Looking for a place to camp, priorities were a low-lying spot in a local valley, protecting me from the worst of the wind and snow, with walking access to the Brecon&rsquo;s highest peaks.</p>

<h2>Wild Camping at Cwm Llwch</h2>

<p>Hunting online for hints to wild camping sites in the Brecons, wild campers are reluctant to give exact locations on public forums due to fears about overuse, yielded an excellent suggestion along the Nant Cwm Llwch river, south from Llyn Cwm Llwch, a small lake beneath Pen Y Fan.</p>

<p>Looking for further information about the location, led me to realising I had  been there before! It&rsquo;s the Race HQ for the Pen Y Fan Fell Race, day one in the <a href="http://www.breconfans.org.uk/">Brecon Fans Race Weekend</a>. This was my first ever fell race, in a very short fell running career (the second race the following day was my last!).</p>

<p>The site comes with permission from the farmer to wild camp there, for a very modest payment in the morning (£3 pppn), which allows you to relax on the usual &ldquo;wild camping rules&rdquo; e.g. pitching your tent at dusk, leaving at sunrise and not leaving tents pitched during the day. They also allow open camp fires, an activity normally violating the &ldquo;leave no trace&rdquo; ethic when wild camping on open access land. The Nant Cwm Llwch river curves around the site, providing easy access to water. Cars can be safely parked near the entrance gate.</p>

<p>Continuing onward along the track leading into the field, you can follow the river straight to its source, the secluded lake hiding at the foot of the northern face of Pen Y Fan. Well-worn paths from the lake guide you up to the ridge around this rock hollow, carved out during a previous glacial era, and onwards to popular peaks, Corn Du and Pen Y Fan.</p>

<p>Overall, the location easily justifies the small payment required to stay there. Heading further up towards the lake, there are plenty of spaces to wild camp without permission (and payment) but you lose the ability to have open fires and leaving tents pitched during the day, etc.</p>

<p>During my stay, there was only one other solitary camper in the area and it definitely felt &ldquo;wild&rdquo; enough. Returning from my walk the next day, there were half a dozen cars parked by other walkers along the entrance. It&rsquo;s easy to imagine, during the summer, this pitch would be busy, with cars parked and people camping, that it would lose the &ldquo;wild camping&rdquo; feeling. This wasn&rsquo;t a problem camping during January (sub-zero temperatures seem to keep people away&hellip;)!</p>

<p><strong>There&rsquo;s no official information about this site online, in proper wild camping style, here&rsquo;s the grid reference: SO 00656 24449</strong>.</p>

<p>Ground temperatures were falling to freezing overnight, wind chill was definitely going to take it below zero. Definitely a night for a tent over a bivy bag! Perfect opportunity for testing the <a href="http://www.livefortheoutdoors.com/Gear-Reviews/Search-Results/Tents/Vango-Apex-200-2013/">Vango Apex 200</a>.</p>

<h2>Vango Apex 200</h2>

<p>Lightweight adventure two-man tent, although it&rsquo;s more one man and gear, weighing in at 1.7 kg. Small enough to pack inside a thirty litre rucksack.</p>

<p>Pitching instructions were straightforward. Once the tent had been fully pegged out, the tension-band system can be connected to provide extra stability during high winds. Unnecessary during my trip, but tent seemed rock solid with this additional support. Looking forward to a proper field test in bad weather.</p>

<p>Head room&rsquo;s tight, being over six foot, but felt fairly spacious apart from that. Small porch provides a cooking area during bad weather or space for storing your boots.</p>

<p>Pegs included with the tent were poor, too short and didn&rsquo;t appear very robust. Wouldn&rsquo;t trust them to hold guy lines in high winds. Usable as ground sheet pegs, providing the ground was soft. Replaced guy line pegs with <a href="http://www.cleats.co.uk/browse-by-product/tent-pegs/cl622-alloy-y-tent-peg-pack-of-6.html">titanium Y spikes</a> for additional stability.</p>

<p>With tent pitched, dinner cooked and darkness closing in it was time to retire to the warmth of my sleeping bag.</p>

<h2>Winter Camping Setup</h2>

<p>With sub-zero temperatures due overnight, this was the first real test of my  winter sleeping gear, painstakingly hunted down from Ebay over the summer. Sleeping bag was an early version of the current <a href="http://www.facewest.co.uk/Mountain-Equipment-Snowline.html">Mountain Equipment Snowline</a>. Used this on top of the <a href="http://www.exped.com/usa/en/product-category/mats/synmat-7-m">Exped Synmat 7</a> inflatable sleeping mattress.</p>

<p>Sleeping bag and mat coped comfortably with the temperatures. Woke up at 4am to discover feeling far too hot, had to open side zips on the sleeping bag to cool down! Both items have a low temperature rating of -17 c, giving me confidence using the same set-up on even colder nights.</p>

<p>Opening the entrance in the morning, revealed a light covering of snow on the ground, which indicated heavier dumps on the surrounding peaks. Leaning out from my micro-climate, stove was started to boil water for my luxury breakfast - instant porridge and &ldquo;3 in 1&rdquo; coffee mix.</p>

<h2>Best laid plans&hellip;</h2>

<p>Plan had been to walk to the lake, tracing the path up around the rim and then along to the <a href="http://www.walkscene.co.uk/description_51/Brecon_Four_Peaks_Corn_Du_Pen_y_Fan_Cribyn_Fan_y_Big.html">four peaks</a> (Corn Du, Pen Y Fan, Cribyn, Fan Y Big) before returning home on the same path. Unfortunately, the weather had over ideas&hellip;</p>

<p>Walking along the river towards Pen Y Fan, the path climbs slowly through fields with sheep and past farm buildings until hitting the boundary fence marking &ldquo;open access land&rdquo;. Snow covering the hills started to become deeper above 400 metres, paths and streams disappearing. Low-lying cloud swallowed the peaks above.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-d-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpa1/v/t1.0-9/10858542_10155145828500092_7373410459009224363_n.jpg?oh=ef54f25fca95c58b8cadc3d53662e1e3&amp;oe=5591F493&amp;__gda__=1431607429_fa907312d4ee7fd8cb1c0e853932757e">https://fbcdn-sphotos-d-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpa1/v/t1.0-9/10858542_10155145828500092_7373410459009224363_n.jpg?oh=ef54f25fca95c58b8cadc3d53662e1e3&amp;oe=5591F493&amp;__gda__=1431607429_fa907312d4ee7fd8cb1c0e853932757e</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Reaching the lake, the briefest of indentations on the westerly hills, now covered with thick snow, gave away where the path once lay. Plunging through  snow up to my knees, the increasing gradient made a tough climb to the rim surrounding the lake.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-h-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10959905_10155145827890092_2343075930456606222_n.jpg?oh=572ba94c2d54357b7d35040446bf0449&amp;oe=5593E3B3&amp;__gda__=1431853004_da68b6cbaec2d40c08fcb4acdfab982a">https://fbcdn-sphotos-h-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10959905_10155145827890092_2343075930456606222_n.jpg?oh=572ba94c2d54357b7d35040446bf0449&amp;oe=5593E3B3&amp;__gda__=1431853004_da68b6cbaec2d40c08fcb4acdfab982a</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Path followed the bowl&rsquo;s rim, passing Tommy Jones Obelisk. Snow covering the path turned into ice.</p>

<p>Crampons came out.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-g-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10009747_10155145828035092_3127775100337108775_n.jpg?oh=775d5bac5c6252e38d417672667eb87c&amp;oe=555AC4FC&amp;__gda__=1435883395_0b5654d0e20b73270a5d5458eeb9fb49">https://fbcdn-sphotos-g-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10009747_10155145828035092_3127775100337108775_n.jpg?oh=775d5bac5c6252e38d417672667eb87c&amp;oe=555AC4FC&amp;__gda__=1435883395_0b5654d0e20b73270a5d5458eeb9fb49</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Strong winds funnelled up the valley over the edge, blowing spindrift everywhere. Forecast wind speeds were thirty, gusting to over forty, miles per hour. Snow goggles made a huge difference.</p>

<p>Reaching the cloud base, visibility dropped further.</p>

<p>Heading along the Craig Cwm Llwch ridge, conditions deteriorated. Gusts of wind, rising in intensity, meant staying upright became difficult.</p>

<p>After half a kilometre struggling onwards, with two hundred metres to the first summit, I made the decision to turn around.</p>

<p>Severe winds, full-on winter conditions and being alone had made me begun to feel uncomfortable continuing. Forecasts predicted increasing wind speeds throughout the day.</p>

<p>Recorded a short video of the conditions before reversing the path back down to the lake.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G3fEDNIGa78" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Slowly retracting my foot steps, conditions back at the tent were a different world, the overnight snow melted and calm winds.</p>

<p>Looking back towards Pen Y Fan, the afternoon had brought an unexpected calm to the weather. Summits free from cloud, the sun breaking through and a lull in the winds. How annoying!</p>

<p>Throwing the unpacked tent in the car boot, driving home earlier than planned meant being back in time to watch the football.</p>

<p>Wild camping in winter has advantages compared to the summer months. Trips have a more adventurous feel, you&rsquo;re unlikely to be sharing popular spots with others and later sunrises mean you can get a lie in! Warmer sleeping bag and mat, extra clothes for the evening and you can extend &ldquo;sleeping under canvas&rdquo; to all four seasons.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
