<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bleaklow | Everything Else.]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/categories/bleaklow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-19T15:42:43+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Navigation - Bleaklow]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/2015/03/19/winter-navigation-bleaklow/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-19T09:39:14+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.jamesthom.as/blog/2015/03/19/winter-navigation-bleaklow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/10982490_10100164397395871_2816996236474834286_n.jpg?oh=2767b19a56218ae3d9b29ec96ff25c01&amp;oe=557E2FF7">https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/10982490_10100164397395871_2816996236474834286_n.jpg?oh=2767b19a56218ae3d9b29ec96ff25c01&amp;oe=557E2FF7</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Visiting Manchester last month presented an opportunity for a weekend walk in the Peak District. Winter had returned with a vengeance that week, with heavy snow across the National Park. People were skiing down the face of Mam Tor and ice climbing up Kinder Downfall. Definitely not a regular occurrence&hellip;</p>

<p>Recent trips to the Peak District have concentrated on Kinder Scout, the popular moorland plateau between Manchester and Sheffield. Looking for something more remote, Bleaklow was an obvious choice.</p>

<p>Bleaklow&rsquo;s a <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bleaklow">&ldquo;peat covered, gritstone moorland, just north of Kinder Scout, across the Snake Pass (A57), in the Derbyshire High Peak near the town of Glossop. Much of it is nearly 2,000 feet (610 m) above sea level and it is the source of the River Derwent.&rdquo;</a></em></p>

<p>Bleaklow feels far more remote than Kinder Scout. Fewer walkers visit the area. Large expanses of featureless moorland, with deep peat groughs and without a plateau edge like Kinder, can make the area extremely disorientating.</p>

<p>Navigating across the moorland can be a challenge during summer. Winter conditions, with deep snow and ice, provided a great opportunity to practice my navigation skills further.</p>

<h2>Planned Route</h2>

<iframe src='https://connect.garmin.com/activity/embed/699538547' width='465' height='500' frameborder='0'></iframe>


<p>Starting at Glossop, parking near Mill Pond, we planned to head up Yellow Slacks clough, following the ridge to Dog Rock. Continuing along Dowstone Clough before turning south to find Lower and Upper Shelf Stones. From the trig point above Higher Shelf Stones, walking north-east to Hern Stones. Walking north from here to Wain Stones and Bleaklow Head, stopping for lunch.</p>

<p>Returning along the Pennine Way, past Hern Stones and Hern Clough, until the crossing with Doctor&rsquo;s Gate. We would then follow this path back along the brook to our starting location.</p>

<p><em>Well, that was the plan&hellip;</em></p>

<h2>Best Laid Plans&hellip;</h2>

<p>Arriving at Glossop, there was no snow on the ground but the surrounding hills were a different story. Heading along the river, opposite Shire Hill, until we verved off the path up Shittern Clough to the ridge above Yellow Slacks.</p>

<p>Getting above four hundred metres, the moorland began to disappear under a thin covering of snow. The depth increased as we climbed higher, ankle deep above five hundred metres.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-e-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/10983422_10155171663475092_1487896897203765697_n.jpg?oh=fcb51e54d610d18a53cd239a31f93b34&amp;oe=5580F865&amp;__gda__=1437530368_e5e7b6e48c43eda0c689deb4e60d03d0">https://fbcdn-sphotos-e-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/10983422_10155171663475092_1487896897203765697_n.jpg?oh=fcb51e54d610d18a53cd239a31f93b34&amp;oe=5580F865&amp;__gda__=1437530368_e5e7b6e48c43eda0c689deb4e60d03d0</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Hitting Dog Rock, we rose above the low cloud base, covering the landscape with a thick clag. We couldn&rsquo;t see further than fifty to seventy metres in any direction.</p>

<p>We had planned to <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/aiming-off.shtml">hand-rail</a> the fence along Dowstone Clough until it ended, and then walk on a bearing to the Trig Point at Higher Shelf Stones.</p>

<h3>Snow covered moorland</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, the fence didn&rsquo;t seem to exist any more.</p>

<p>There was a series of  fence posts, now partially obscured by the snow, indicating where the fence once stood. These posts became more infrequent before disappearing altogether.</p>

<p>This fence was parallel to the brook running up Dowstone Clough, making it an obvious <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/aiming-off.shtml">handrail</a> substitute. We decided to follow the river much further along, before hitting a prominent fork, before turning off for the Trig Point.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/1505470_10155171663825092_4397147666091263027_n.jpg?oh=2ef40c6f00d3d71f1f5e0ca97c4e75b7&amp;oe=557D42CF">https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xfp1/v/t1.0-9/1505470_10155171663825092_4397147666091263027_n.jpg?oh=2ef40c6f00d3d71f1f5e0ca97c4e75b7&amp;oe=557D42CF</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>We would have to <a href="http://www.mcofs.org.uk/estimating-distance-travelled.asp">pace out</a> the distance to the Trig Point due to the lack of other navigational features.</p>

<p>Continuing along the <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/aiming-off.shtml">handrail</a>, rather than stopping at the fence end, reduced the length of our next navigation leg, from over a kilometre to five hundred metres.</p>

<p>The landscape was now expansive moorland, crossed by deep peat groughs, covered with thick snow. Traversing up and down these trenches, with snow drifts up to your waist, made accurate <a href="http://www.mcofs.org.uk/estimating-distance-travelled.asp">pacing</a> difficult.</p>

<p><em>Reducing the length of each navigation leg would help to counter this challenge.</em></p>

<p>With the snow obscuring <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/ticking-off-features.shtml">tick-off features</a>, e.g. connecting streams, along our handrail, we resorted to using timing to confirm the fork we reached was correct.</p>

<p>Taking a bearing to the Trig Point, we set off pacing the distance to Higher Shelf Stones.</p>

<h3>Higher Shelf Stones</h3>

<p>Counting double-paces to measure hundred metre intervals, we continued for five hundred metres before hitting&hellip; <strong>nothing.</strong></p>

<p>Later on, reviewing my GPS trace of the route, we had drifted slightly to the east. Poor visibility meant we were unable to find it from a quick visual search. Assuming we were somewhere to the east or west of the location, we walked due east for hundred metres and then reversed our steps for two hundred metres west. Here we hit the Upper Shelf Stones and then found the Trig Point.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xap1/t31.0-8/10959917_10155171664230092_4011153869465993755_o.jpg">https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xap1/t31.0-8/10959917_10155171664230092_4011153869465993755_o.jpg</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Due to the lack of significant elevation change on the surrounding ground, we had to try both directions before finding our target.</p>

<p><em>We could have prevented this error, using the <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/aiming-off.shtml">&ldquo;aiming off&rdquo;</a> technique when taking our bearing.</em></p>

<p>Given the challenges finding the Trig Point, we decided to change the target for the next navigation leg. Heading for the Pennine Way would prove easier to find, being a well-established paved path, rather than the Hern Stones.</p>

<h3>Finding the Pennine Way</h3>

<p>Pacing and timing were used to navigate over the bearing for seven hundred metres.</p>

<p>It would normally take <a href="http://www.mcofs.org.uk/estimating-distance-travelled.asp">sixty paces, and seventy two seconds, to cover one hundred metres of flat ground at a normal walking speed</a>.</p>

<p>Scrambling up and down deep snow banks whilst stopping every fifty metres to find a new <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/aiming-off.shtml">attack point</a>, had an affect on the accuracy of my pacing and timing calculations.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-h-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10858393_10155171665565092_8759069232056536006_n.jpg?oh=6601a5a227b69c43e9a29a10b46ea8cc&amp;oe=557D4816&amp;__gda__=1438109033_3bcb9216949ce25b84dd049d488bb328">https://fbcdn-sphotos-h-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10858393_10155171665565092_8759069232056536006_n.jpg?oh=6601a5a227b69c43e9a29a10b46ea8cc&amp;oe=557D4816&amp;__gda__=1438109033_3bcb9216949ce25b84dd049d488bb328</a>&#8221;></p>

<p><strong>Not taking this into account led to overestimating the distance we walked and making a &ldquo;parallel error&rdquo;.</strong></p>

<p>Hitting our estimated distance, we came across a wide peat grough with a fork further north. This description matched the river we were expecting, which was actually fifty metres further east, running alongside the Pennine Way.</p>

<p>The snow-covered landscape wiped out all existing paths. This meant we couldn&rsquo;t use the Pennine Way as an additional feature to confirm our location. Without the snow, the missing path would have confirmed we were in the wrong place.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-e-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10968299_10155171664730092_3576614597550349222_n.jpg?oh=70189cdf54699c0e6f8994750271f302&amp;oe=55B2F080&amp;__gda__=1433406463_7cc32603498d180a9daab41ecae59130">https://fbcdn-sphotos-e-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10968299_10155171664730092_3576614597550349222_n.jpg?oh=70189cdf54699c0e6f8994750271f302&amp;oe=55B2F080&amp;__gda__=1433406463_7cc32603498d180a9daab41ecae59130</a>&#8221;></p>

<p><em>We were now further west than we realised.</em></p>

<p>Next stop was the Wain Stones, without the Pennine Way to follow, we had to walk north on a bearing. Having learnt from our previous difficulty finding the Trig Point, we <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/aiming-off.shtml">&ldquo;aimed off&rdquo;</a> to the east. Using the prominent stones around Bleaklow Head as a <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/catching-features.shtml">&ldquo;catching feature&rdquo;</a> to ensure we didn&rsquo;t walk too far, before turning west.</p>

<p>Fortunately, we <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/aiming-off.shtml">&ldquo;aimed off&rdquo;</a> by a greater distance than our earlier error. Heading for one hundred metres east of the Wain Stones, which ended up being fifty metres, but still further east enabling us to hit our <a href="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/safety/catching-features.shtml">catching feature</a>.</p>

<h3>Lunch at Wain Stones</h3>

<p>Stopping for lunch at Wain Stones, the sun began to break through the low-lying cloud.</p>

<p>Bringing camping stoves meant we were treated to freshly cooked bacon baguettes and hot coffee. Definitely an improvement over squashed sandwiches and lukewarm tea! Chris also brought the radio to listen to the Arsenal vs Tottenham match.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-g-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10968372_10155171664830092_9161828737790974782_n.jpg?oh=f1679818111ef1367d195a4f94f2cd09&amp;oe=557FCD2A&amp;__gda__=1437796181_0bb5c0e234fcbdf8ca28d62558f9d7cd">https://fbcdn-sphotos-g-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xpf1/v/t1.0-9/10968372_10155171664830092_9161828737790974782_n.jpg?oh=f1679818111ef1367d195a4f94f2cd09&amp;oe=557FCD2A&amp;__gda__=1437796181_0bb5c0e234fcbdf8ca28d62558f9d7cd</a>&#8221;></p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xft1/v/t1.0-9/10393972_10155171664960092_4427453912132848285_n.jpg?oh=94f96c0db850015a167b814283a28213&amp;oe=55B43CF8">https://scontent-lhr.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-xft1/v/t1.0-9/10393972_10155171664960092_4427453912132848285_n.jpg?oh=94f96c0db850015a167b814283a28213&amp;oe=55B43CF8</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>With the sun shining, football on the radio and breakfast cooking, Bleaklow felt for a brief moment, less, well, bleak.</p>

<p>Half an hour later, we started our walk back home.</p>

<h3>Heading Home</h3>

<p>Following a bearing south for nearly two kilometres, we were heading for Crooked Clough as a linear feature to intercept. The brook was significant enough to be visible even with the heavy snow. Estimating our time to cover the distance allowed us to double-check our location.</p>

<p>Heading away from Bleaklow Head, we came across one of the many aircraft wreckages on the moor. It was an eerie sight, the snow-covered aircraft strewn across the land.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://fbcdn-sphotos-f-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xap1/v/t1.0-9/1456032_10100164397834991_6635012036973711340_n.jpg?oh=d0ac383db97950457cf4c0e7ebafa20c&amp;oe=55BA05D9&amp;__gda__=1437438688_e7a54ca17ab6dc674ab163ae18ec8645">https://fbcdn-sphotos-f-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-xap1/v/t1.0-9/1456032_10100164397834991_6635012036973711340_n.jpg?oh=d0ac383db97950457cf4c0e7ebafa20c&amp;oe=55BA05D9&amp;__gda__=1437438688_e7a54ca17ab6dc674ab163ae18ec8645</a>&#8221;></p>

<p>Bleaklow was definitely felt very remote during our trip. We didn&rsquo;t see another person all day, closest we came was once hearing faint voices somewhere out there through the clag.</p>

<p>Sun continued to break through the cloud as we headed home. This increased visibility and with an easier route coming back, navigation was much simpler on the return leg.</p>

<p>Arriving at Crooked Clough, we followed the ridge along until the Doctor&rsquo;s Gate path finally came into view. Dropping down, following the river, the snow began to disappear and we even got a blue sky!</p>

<p>Less than an hour later, we were back at the car. Definitely felt like returning to the normal world after the remote, snow-covered landscape of Bleaklow.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>We had a fantastic day walking in the more remote areas of the Peak District. While you may be only ten kilometres from civilisation, the vast open moorland in winter conditions feels extremely remote, desolate and wild.</p>

<p>Successfully navigating challenging conditions gives you a great sense of accomplishment. It&rsquo;s great to put those skills you practice during good weather and visibility to use for real. Trips to the Lake District, Snowdonia and the Brecon Beacons during the winter has given me opportunities to build my confidence walking and navigating safely under winter conditions.</p>

<p>Looking back at this trip, there&rsquo;s a number of useful hints to consider when planning a route during difficult conditions.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reduce leg distances.</strong> Having more route legs, with shorter distances between them, will allow you to reduce the chance of errors. Navigational drift increases the further you walk. Walking long distances on a bearing is easier when you have great visibility and lots of terrain features to confirm your position.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Heavy snow will wipe out smaller terrain features.</strong> Paths, streams and fences can all be covered. We mistakenly assumed the Pennine Way would be visible.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pacing and time across uneven terrain.</strong> Make sure you adjust the pacing and timing counts for the condition underfoot. We should have added extra paces to the pace count for the undulating terrain and decreased our estimated walking speed significantly.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Use attack points that are unlikely to change</strong>, i.e significant terrain features. Fences get removed, streams dry up, forests are cut down. The fence we saw on the map, was no more!</p></li>
<li><p><strong>GPS as a backup.</strong> We did have a GPS for recording our route and emergency use. However, we could used it for confirming our location at important points, e.g. when we made the parallel error, or when re-locating. Winter conditions make the consequences of a mistake much greater, it&rsquo;s worth having this tool available.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
